Ludmil A. Chotkowski papers 1916-2005 CPAA 90-14
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Ludmil A.Chotkowski Papers
1982-1989
Chotkowski, Ludmil A., 1916-2005
CPAA 90-14
5 boxes (2.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
The papers of Ludmil A. Chotkowski, a Polish American physician and vice-president of the Solidarity International, Connecticut Chapter, a grass root organization supporting underground and dissident activities in Poland in the 1980s. He initiated a successful campaign to erect the Popieluszko Human Rights Monument in New Britain, Conn. He was involved in lobbying efforts and media campaigns on behalf of Polish opposition and participated in activities of other anti-communist and pro-democracy organizations based in the USA.
Biographical Note
Ludmil Adam Chotkowski, M.D. - born in Kensington, Conn. on May 19th, 1916 died on October 6th, 2005. he held a BS from Trinity College (1938), and a MD from Yale University (1942). He served with USAR Medical Corps from 1942 to 1944. Dr. Chotkowski, an internist, practiced in Berlin, Conn. and served as a state medical examiner, police surgeon, school physician and health director. He initiated many projects related to public health and environmental safety. He was an early crusader for open-space and anti-sprawl conservation efforts. In the 1980s he was one of the founders of and then vice-president and spokesman of a grass-root organization called the Solidarity International, Connecticut Chapter; co-chairman of Popieluszko Human Rights Monument Committee in New Britain in 1984-1989; a participant of the International Human Rights Conference in Krakow in 1988; and active in several human rights, pro-democracy and anti-communist organizations in the US.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Collection contains materials related to the Solidarity International Connecticut Chapter, one of the many American and Western European grass-root organizations that supported Polish underground Solidarity movement and operated between 1982 and 1989. Among Solidarity International initiatives documented in this collection are: media campaigns, political lobbying and fundraising, erection of Popieluszko Human Right Monument in New Britain, Conn. And donation of Mercedes-Benz van for Lech Walesa. The collection also includes documents from the International Human Rights Conference in Krakow, Poland in 1988 and Mr. Chotkowski meeting with Lech Walesa; materials related to his involvement in several American anti-communist or pro-democracy organizations targeting other regions of the world. Materials include: correspondence, financial records, press releases, clippings, statements, programs, minutes, audiotapes, videotape, a medal, and a model of Popieluszko monument.
The collection is open for research.
Gift of Ludomil A. Chotkowski,1990
Search Terms
Solidarity International. Connecticut Chapter.; Chotkowski, Ludomil A, 1916-2005.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut --Political activities -- 20th century.; Popieluszko, Jerzy, 1947-1984 -- Monuments -- Connecticut -- New Britain.; International Human Rights Conference (1988: Krakow, Poland).; Connecticut; Correspondence; Interviews; Clippings; Financial records; Minutes; Photographs; Videotapes
Related Material
Andre B. Blaszczynski Papers CPAA 87-105
Elizabeth Wasiutynski Papers CPAA 87-115
Person to Person Project Records CPAA 87-08
- Solidarity International, Connecticut Chapter, 1982-1989; 2.5 linear ft.
  - L.A. Chotkowski: copy of passport, obituaries, other biographical information, 198?-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter to Prof. S.A. Blejwas concerning the donation of the papers, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - L.A. Chotkowski speeches and notes to speeches, 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Solidarity International, Connecticut Chapter [of Connecticut, Inc.] - certificate of incorporation, by-laws, drafts, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mailing lists, contacts (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Press releases, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Activities, related announcements and correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Financial statements, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Solidarity International, Inc., New York, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Peace Conference organized by Solidarity International, Connecticut Chapter, New Britain, Oct.20, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence related to Solidarity International, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with US Presidents related to Solidarity International, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Connecticut senators and representatives to the US Congress related to Solidarity International, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Resolutions related to human rights in Poland and Eastern Europe, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Human rights issues, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Appeals, statements, reports from Polish underground (translated into English), 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Andrzej Gwiazda visit, press releases, clippings, photo, July, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mercedes-Benz van for Lech Walesa, correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - SOS (Support of Solidarity), Boston, newsletter, press releases, flyers, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations (CSSO), proposal, letter of agreement, resolutions, minutes, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lech Walesa "Address to a Joint Meeting of the Congress of the USA, Nov.15, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Relations of Polish Americans with the Communist regime in Poland, position paper of the Polish American Congress, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Audiotape - meeting with U.S. Rep. Nancy Johnson, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Audiotape - "What is going on in Poland" in radio program "Perspectives" host: Brian Thomas, guest: L.A.Chotkowski, 8/25/1989 on WTIC, ca. 20 minutes (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Audiotape - interview with L.A.Chotkowski on political situation in Poland, WPOP, 8/16/1989, ca.15 minutes (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Audiotape - Side A: statements on Solidarity and Polish economic matters by L.A.Chotkowski, R.Kosinski, Stanislaus A.Blejwas, WPOP Channel 3 Eyewitness News, 1983. Side B:statements by L.A.Chotkowski after kidnapping and murder of Father Jerzy Popieluszko; Zbigniew Brzezinski on trial of murderers of Father Jerzy Popieluszko, 1985, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Andre Blaszczynski, "Economic relations with Poland and USSR in light of delegalization of Solidarity", ca. 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Poland Two Years Later", transcript of MacNeil- Lehrer Report, Aug., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, donations and bank books, financial records, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, New Britain Parks and Recreation Department correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, blueprints, correspondence, fundraising, publicity, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Eddy Roger, candidate for US Senate, and his financial contribution to the Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, press clippings, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, dedication program, New Britain, CT, June 11, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Popieluszko Human Rights Monument, photos, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Audiotape - Side A: Human Rights Monument Committee, 1985, reports by Walter Grymek, Richard Kosinski, Stan Gruszka, L.A.Chotkowski, Side B: Second Anniversary of Solidarity, statements by L.A.Chotkowski and E.Wasiutynski, CBS News, 1983, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Videotape: Human Rights Monument, host: Henry Okolica, guest: L.A.Chotkowski, Channel 30 "Jewish Live" 6/15/86, ca. 20 minutes, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Audiotape - Side A: Human Rights Monument Committee, reports, [meeting at Polish National Home?] 1986 Side B: MacNeal-Lehrer News 1983, host: Robert Lehrer, guests: Jan Nowak and others, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sikorska, Grazyna "Jerzy Popieluszko a Martyr for the Truth." Grand Rapids, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles about Father Jerzy Popieluszko, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photos of Popieluszko's grave and parish in Warsaw, Poland, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Human Rights conference, Krakow, Poland, speeches, resolutions, August, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Human Rights abuses in Poland underground publications, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - " 2 audiotapes: No. 1: Polish Heritage Radio Program,Fairfield, 1988: side A - Interview with Elizabeth Wasiutynski about International Human Rights Conference in Krakow and The Coordinating Office Abroad NSZZ Solidarnosc in Brussels; side B - Interview with Ludmil A.Chotkowski about the International Human Rights Conference in Krakow and the meeting with Lech Walesa No.2: side A an interview with L.A.Chotkowski for Connecticut News, WPOP station, 1988 about International Human Rights Conference in Krakow and meeting with Lech Walesa. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Violation of the Helsinki Accords in Poland since Dec.13, 1981. A Helsinki Watch Report Feb.1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Violations of the Helsinki Accords. A report to the Helsinki Review Conference Madrid, Nov. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Audiotape- American Leadership Conference in Washington, 5/2/87; Side A: Don Griffes "Education and Constitution", Side B: L.A. Chotkowski "Stopping Soviet expansion", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Union of Capeverdeans for an Independent Democracy-conference July, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Freedom Federation: a statement purpose, by-laws, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Central America, human rights matters, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - CAUSA (Confederation of the Associations for the Unification of the Societates of the Americas)- International Ministerial Alliance - correspondence, news releases, related clippings, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clippings in English and Polish undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Polish American community: flyers, publications, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cyran, Andrzej "Political comment: truth vs. untruth", undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - M. Wasilewski "The Psychological roots of communism", with dedication to Dr. Chotkowski, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Listy do Polakow" two issues include letters related to Solidarity International, March-May, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Contemporary Poland in historical perspective" an international conference, Yale University, speeches by Stanislaw Gomulka, Wlodzimierz Brus, Aleksander Smolar, Wojciech Karpinski, Joseph Rothschild, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlet "Soviet strategic defense programs", by the US Department of State and Department of Defense, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - President Ronald Reagan's visit to New Britain, 2 photos of L.A. Chotkowski among spectators, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photo of Sen. Chris Dodd with Lech Walesa with senator's dedication for L.A. Chotkowski, ca. 1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Artifacts: 3-D model of Popieluszko Human Rights Monument signed "HFC '86"; dimensions: flame-like structure 35 cm high on 26 x 22 sextagonal base, pedestal: 42 cm in diameter x 5 cm high, filled with rocks and 11.5 x 12.5 cm brass medal in shape of Poland; front: Father Jerzy Popieluszko face with cross imposed over it; reverse: an excerpt from his last sermon delivered in Bydgoszcz on Oct. 19th, 1984, ca. 1985 (Box 5)